I'm Richard Stallman.
أنا ريتشارد ستولمن
25 years ago [in 1983]
منذ 25 سنة [في عام 1983]
I founded the Free Software movement.
أسست حركة البرمجيات الحرة.
Free Software
البرمجيات الحرة
is software that respects users' freedom
إنها برمجيات تحترم حرية المستخدم
and the social solidarity of their community.
والتكافل الإجتماعي لمجتمعهم
Nonfree programs are proprietary software.
البرامج الغير حرة، هي برامج إحتكارية.
That is,
بمعنى،
they take away users' freedom
أنها تسلب المستخدمين من حقوقهم.
keeping them divided and helpless.
وتحفظهم مفرقين بلا قوة.
Divided
مُفرقين
because they are forbidden from sharing the program
لأنه محرم عليهم المشاركة ببرمجياتهم.
and helpless
وبلا قوة
because users don't have the source code of the program.
لأن المستخدم لا يملك الشفرة المصدرية للبرنامج.
That is,
مما يعني،
they cannot change it, they cannot even find out
لا يمكنهم تغير البرنامج، أو حتى معرفة
what the program is really doing,
ماذا يفعل البرنامج بالتحديد،
and it can do very bad things.
ويمكن للبرنامج أن يفعل أشياء سيئة جداً.
Free Software
البرمجيات الحرة
means that the user has 4 essential freedoms:
تعني أن المستخدم يملك 4 حريات أساسية:
Freedom 0
الحرية 0
is the freedom to run the program for any purpose.
هي حرية تشغيل البرنامج لأي غرض.
Freedom 1
الحرية 1
is the freedom to study the source code of the program
حرية دراسة الشفرة المصدرية للبرنامج
and change it to make it do what you wish.
وتعديلها حتى يفعل البرنامج ما يريد هو.
Freedom 2
الحرية 2
is the freedom to help your neighbor;
هي حرية مساعدة الجار؛
that is,
بمعنى،
the freedom to make and distribute
حرية عمل وتوزبع
exact copies of the program whenever you want.
نسخ طبق الأصل وقتما تريد.
And freedom 3
والحرية 3
is the freedom to contribute to your community;
هي حرية المساهمة في المجتمع:
that is,
بمعنى،
the freedom to make and distribute copies
حرية عمل وتوزيع
of your modified versions of the program.
نسخك المعدلة من البرنامج.
With these four freedoms a program is Free Software
بهذه الحريات الأربع يكون البرنامج من البرمجيات الحرة
because the social system for its use and distribution
لأن النظام الإجتماعي لإستخدام البرنامج وتوزيعه
is an ethical system that respects everyone's  freedom
نظام أخلاقي يحترم حرية الأفراد
and the freedom of the community of users.
وحرية مجتمع المستخدمين.
Software must be Free because we all deserve freedom,
يلزم أن تكون البرمجيات حرة لأننا جمبعاً نستحق الحرية،
we all deserve
جميعنا نستحق
to be allowed to  participate in a free community.
الفرصة للمشاركة في مجتمع حر.
Therefore,
لذلك،
schools should teach only Free Software.
على المدارس أن تُدَرِس فقط البرمجيات الحرة.
There are four reasons why this is so.
هناك أبعة أسباب تحتم ذلك.
The most shallow reason is to save money.
السبب ألأكثر سطحية هو توفير النقود.
Schools don't have enough money,
المدارس لا تملك التمويل الكافي،
so they shouldn't waste their money
لذلك عليهم ألا يهدروا النقود
paying for permission to use proprietary software.
أنفاقاً على رخص لإستخدام البرمجيات الحكرية.
This is an obvious reason,
هذا سبب بديهي،
but some proprietary software companies
ولكن بعض شركات البرمجيات الحكرية
usually eliminate this shallow reason
عادةً ما تبطل هذا السبب السطحي
by donating copies of their proprietary programs
بأن تتبرع بنسخ من برمجياتها الحكرية
to the schools at no charge or at a small price.
للمدارس بدون مقابل أو مقابل رمزي.
The reason why they do that is to get students addicted.
والسبب في ذلك حتى يدمن الطلاب برامجهم.
It's a malicious plan.
إنها خطة خبيثة.
It's a plan to use schools as instruments to impose
إنها خطة لإستغلال مدارسنا كأدوات لفرض
a permanent dependence on students.
إعتمادية دائمة لدى الطلبة.
If a school teaches how to use a proprietary program,
إذا علمت المدرسة كيفية إستخدام البرمجيات الإحتكارية،
the student will be dependent on that program,
سيعتمد التلاميذ على البرمجيات الإحتكارية،
and after he graduates
وبعد التخرج
he will have to pay to use that program.
سيكون عليه أن يدفع مقابل إستخدامه لهذه البرمجيات.
He will probably work for a company
غالبا سيعمل في شركة
that does not receive copies of the program free of charge.
لا تحصل على نسخة مجانية لهذه البرمجيات.
Therefore,
وعليه،
proprietary software developers use schools
مطوري البرمجيات الإحتكارية يستغلون مدارسنا
to impose permanent dependence on the whole society.
لفرض إعتمادية دائمة على كل المجتمع.
Schools must refuse
على المدارس رفض
to participate in such a malicious plan
المشاركة في مثل هذه الخطط الخبيثة
because schools have a social mission,
لأن المدارس لديها مهمة إجتماعية،
which is to educate the next generation to be good citizens
أن يعلِّموا الجيل القادم من المواطنين الصالحين
of a capable, strong, independent, cooperating and
لمجتمع قادر، قوي، مستقل، متعاون،
free society.
وحر.
This can only be achieved by teaching Free Software.
وتدريس البرمجيات الحرة هي الطريقة الوحيدة لتحقيق ذلك.
Schools must eliminate, delete proprietary software
يتوجب على المدارس التخلص من، ومحو البرمجيات الإحتكارية
and install Free Software.
وتحميل البرمجيات الحرة.
But there is  a deeper reason:
لكن يوجد سبب أعمق:
to form good programmers,
لتنشيئة مطورين جيدين،
because in order to learn good programming skills
ولأنه لتعلم مهارات برمجة جيدة
students need to read lots of code and write lots of code.
على الطلبة الإطلاع على أكواد كثيرة ويكتبون أكواد كثيرة.
To learn to write good code for big programs
ليتعلموا أن يكتبوا أكواد جيدة لمشاكل كبيرة
students need to write small changes
على الطلبة أن يكتبوا تعديلات صغيرة
in the code of big programs.
في أكواد المشاكل الكبيرة.
All this is possible only with Free Software.
الكل ممكن فقط مع البرمجيات الحرة
Only Free Software
فقط البرمجيات الحرة
allows education in information technology.
تسمح بتدريس تكنولوجيا المعلومات.
But there is still a deeper reason:
لكن لازال هناك سبب أعمق:
to teach good citizenship,
لتعليم المواطنة الصالحة،
because schools have the mission to teach
لأن المدارس لديها مهمة تدريس
not only facts and technical skills, but above all
ليس فقط الحقائق والمهارات الفنية، ولكن فوق الكل
the spirit of good will, the habit of helping others.
روح الإرادة الصالحة، وعادة مساعدة الآخرين.
Therefore, each class should have this rule:
لذلك، على كل فصل أن يتضمن هذه القاعدة:
"students, if you bring a program to the class,
"عزيزي الطالب/الطالبة، إذا أحضرت برنامج إلى الفصل،
you can't keep it for yourself,
لا يمكنك الإحتفاظ به لنفسك،
you must share it with the rest of the class."
يتوجب عليك مشاركته مع باقي الفصل"
The school should practice what it preaches,
على المدرسة أن تمارس ما تنادي به،
it should introduce only Free Software in the classroom.
عليها أن تقدم البرمجيات الحرة في قاعات الفصول.
All schools should migrate to Free Software
على المدسة أن تمارس ما تنادي به،
and teach exclusively
وتدرس حصرياً البرمجيات الحرة
because each school should participate
لأنه على كل مدرسة أن تشارك
in leading society towards freedom and social solidarity.
في قيادة المجتمع نحو الحرية والتماسك المجتمعي.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.